Regional planning collection (James W. Wilson collector)
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Regional planning collection (James W. Wilson collector)
1952 - 1988
F-132
Q106659315
63 cm of textual records 49 photographs
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Physical description: 17 photographs located in F-132-2-0-0-14 Physical description: 24 photographs located in F-132-2-0-0-15 Physical description: 8 photographs located in F-132-2-0-0-16
Wilson, James W.
James W. Wilson was a Professor of Geography at SFU, who had served as the first executive director of the Lower Mainland Regional Planning Board and a relocation planner for the Columbia River Power Project in B.C.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the collection is based on its provenance.
James W. Wilson was a Professor of Geography at SFU, who had served as the first executive director of the Lower Mainland Regional Planning Board and a relocation planner for the Columbia River Power Project in B.C.
Collection consists of records and publications collected by James W. Wilson concerning the work of the Lower Mainland Regional Planning Board. Also includes materials about the resettlement project that B.C. Hydro carried out during the Columbia River Project. Includes personal memoirs written by Dr. Wilson as well as annual reports, minutes, newsletters, essays, correspondence, notes, books, surveys, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
The materials were arranged by the archivist.
Wilson, James W.; Lower Mainland Regional Planning Board; BC Hydro; Photographic materials; Textual records; Environment; Natural resources; Politics; Transportation and utilities
The collection was donated by James W. Wilson to the Simon Fraser University Archives in 1996.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals are expected.
For other material relating to the Columbia River Treaty, see collection F-227, The Columbia River Treaty audio collection; this was a lecture series held at SFU in 1974 and includes a talk given by Wilson (see item F-227-1-0-0-0-8 for the recording and file F-227-2-0-0-9 for the transcripts).
The files are open with no restrictions.
Series descriptions and files lists are available. A more complete biographical profile is available in the hard copy version of the finding aid maintained in the Archives Reading Room.
- Lower Mainland regional planning files, 1952 - 1988; F-132-1; 45 cm of textual records
  published
  James Wilson served as the first executive director of the Lower Mainland Regional Planning Board for thirteen years (1951-1964) The Board was one of the first regional planning authorities in Canada and paved the way for further Canadian work in this field.
  Includes Wilson's personal memoir, "The Lower Mainland's Regional Plan: A Retrospective Introduction," as well as reports, correspondence, minutes, publications and other documents.
  - Memoir - The Lower Mainland's Regional Plan: A retrospective introduction, 1988; F-132-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 132-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Reference Book - Lower Mainland Regional Planning Board, 1969; F-132-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 132-1)
  - Annual Reports, 1952 - 1962; F-132-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 132-1)
  - Annual Reports, 1963 - 1967; F-132-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 132-1)
  - Papers, Minutes, Reports, 1966 - 1968; F-132-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 132-1)
  - Correspondence and Reports - Roberts Bank, 1968; F-132-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 132-1)
  - Papers - Publications and Lists, 1969 - 1972; F-132-1-0-0-7
  - Chance and Challenge - A Concept and Plan for the Development Plan of the Lower Mainland Region of British Columbia, 1963; F-132-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 132-1)
  - Publications - ...The Proposed Rosedale-Agassiz Bridge, The Case for the Haig-Agassiz Road, Airports for the Lower Mainland, The Proposed Boundary Bay Industrial Development Plan, 1952 - 1962; F-132-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 132-2)
  - Publications - The Lower Mainland Looks Ahead, Industrial Land Prospects, The Dynamics of Industrial Land Settlement, Outlook on Industry, Planning for a Flood, Community Planning BC, Regional Development on the Columbia River Project, BC Studies, 1952 - 1983; F-132-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 132-2)
  - Publications - The Development of Burnaby Lake, The Greater Vancouver Metropolitan Community, Metropolitan Parks (2 copies), ..Need for River Crossings in ... Central ... Fraser Valley, Metropolitan Parks - A Challenge, Outlook on Industry, 1953 - 1957; F-132-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 132-2)
  - Publications - Future Crossings of the Fraser River, Urban Sprawl, Economic Aspects of Urban Sprawl, The Proposed Boundary Bay Industrial Development Scheme, Public Reactions to "Industrial Land Prospects", What Price Suburbia?, 1955 - 1967; F-132-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 132-2)
  - Publications - Industrial Development in B.C., Park Problems in B.C., A Long-range Look.....to Transportation Policy, The People and The Plan, Intermunicipal Meeting - Proceedings..., 1956 - 1964; F-132-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 132-2)
  - Publications - Housing Studies..., The Urban Frontier, Manufacturing Industry..., Land for Leisure, 1959 - 1961; F-132-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 132-3)
  - Publications - Land for Farming, Land for Living (2 copies), Public Relations to Land for Living (2 copies), 1962 - 1963; F-132-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 132-3)
  - Publications - Countryside to Suburb, Our Southwestern Shores, Population Trends - 1921-1986 technical report, 1963 - 1968; F-132-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 132-3)
  - Publications - Dynamics of Residential Land Settlement, The Urban Frontier, A Regional Parks Plan For the Lower Mainland Region, Summary Report: A Regional Parks Plan For the Lower Mainland Region, 1963 - 1969; F-132-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 132-3)
  - The Official Regional Plan of the Lower Mainland Regional Planning Board, 1966; F-132-1-0-0-18
- Arrow Lakes Resettlement project files, 1964 - 1988; F-132-2; 31 cm of textual records 49 photographs; Physical description: 17 photographs located in F-132-2-0-0-14 Physical description: 24 photographs located in F-132-2-0-0-15 Physical description: 8 photographs located in F-132-2-0-0-16
  Wilson worked for B.C. Hydro for two years (1964-1966) as the relocation planner on the Columbia River Power Project. He helped to establish new communities for the people of the Arrow Lakes region who were displaced by the project. Includes Wilson's personal memoir, "The Columbia River Development: Looking After People in the Way," as well as correspondence, publications, other documents, and photographs.
  - Memoir - The Columbia River Project: Looking after "The People in The Way", 1988; F-132-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 132-3)
  - Books - Continental Waterboy: The Columbia River Controversy, Donald Waterfield; Land Grab: Oliver Buerge versus the Authority, Donald Waterfield, 1970 - 1973; F-132-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 132-3)
  - People In The Way, J.W. Wilson, 1973; F-132-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 132-3)
  - A Regional Development Study for the Arrow Lakes B.C., 1964; F-132-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 132-4)
  - Correspondence - Community Planning DocumentsPublications - Columbia River Treaty Projects - Property Owner's Guide, The New Outlook For The Arrow Lakes, New Communities For the Arrow Lakes, A General Programme For Cemeteries On The Arrow Lakes, New Communities For the Arrow Lakes (Supplementary Report), 1964 - 1966; F-132-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 132-4)
  - Publications - Preliminary Planning Study for the Village Of Nakusp, The Story of Renata 1887-1965, F-132-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 132-4)
  - Columbia Ministries Committee, 1965 - 1967; F-132-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 132-4)
  - Correspondence - Property Compensation Documents (Publications), 1964 - 1970; F-132-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 132-4)
  - Correspondence - Property Compensation Documents, 1970 - 1972; F-132-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 132-4)
  - Correspondence - Resettlement Survey, 1970; F-132-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 132-4)
  - Correspondence - Repeat Survey, 1981; F-132-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 132-4)
  - Publication - Columbia News Letter Issues 1-29, 1964 - 1969; F-132-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 132-5)
  - Correspondence - Arrow Lake News, 1964 - 1970; F-132-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 132-5)
  - Columbia Photographs, 1967 - 1969; F-132-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 132-5)
    Textual records; Photographic materials
  - Columbia Photographs (includes correspondence and publications), 1967 - 1969; F-132-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 132-5)
  - Columbia Photographs (includes publications), 1964 - 1969; F-132-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 132-5)